OK.
Welcome back.
We're going to move away from pre-training now.
And I think we'll get into, in my opinion,
some of the messier parts of language modeling.
I mean, data is always pretty messy,
but I think post-training and everything
that goes along with it is really artisanal in many ways.
So to set the stage, thus far, I think
you can get to a souped up version of GPT-3.
I'm sure you can use more flops, you can get more data.
So you can make something a little bit better than GPT-3.
But ultimately, the amount of utility
you can get from something like GPT-3,
which is a very big, strong base model,
is ultimately a little bit limited.
When we went from GPT-3 to something like ChatGPT,
I'm sure if your first exposure to these systems
was ChatGPT was kind of amazing, if you
go back and interact with GPT-3, you'll be like,
what is this thing?
What is the point of this thing?
And the only thing you could really do with it
was things like copywriting or these fun little tasks,
where you don't really need reliability or instruction
following.
So today, we are going to get from GPT-3 to something that
is getting basically close to ChatGPT.
So this is the very first part that we need.
And in the next lecture, we will go from ChatGPT to GPT o1
or any of the thinking models that we have today.
So those are going to be the two parts.
And the process that will take us from the left to the right
will be a process that usually people call post-training.
And I want to emphasize just how remarkable it is that we
can do instruction following.
Instruction following is this process
of being able to put in a pretty long, complicated prompt
and get back very reasonable answers at the GPT-3 level,
fine-grained control of these systems
was basically impossible.
Like you would put in a bunch of few-shot prompts,
and you'd say, well, if my examples were good enough,
I'd get something reasonable.
In practice, your ability to steer these models is limited.
But once GPT-3.5 and GPT-4 come around,
you start getting these examples of very long programmatic
prompts.
And then the model really one-shotting the whole prompt.
And so what do you really need in order
to get this kind of instruction following to work?
And so pre-training is always important.
It's the basis on which we build all of this.
So if we ignore pre-training and we just
try to train our way to victory, we will get none of the things
that we want.
Absolutely none of it.
So pre-training is critical because it
scales in this very diverse, broad way.
But once we have pre-training, we
have to then extract the kinds of behaviors
that we want out of this kind of primordial soup
that is pre-training.
And to do that, we are going to have
to do much more explicit data collection, much more
explicit steering, and a lot of messy engineering
that in some ways we don't have to do so far.
I mean, the architecture stuff you might think is messy.
I think it really doesn't compare to the messiness
of real world post-training.
And so we're going to go and collect some data,
or we will talk as if we are going
to go and collect some data.
We're going to talk about what that data looks like,
how to train with it, and what the scale of that looks like.
And I will preface the rest of this lecture
and say, information about frontier post-training
is honestly pretty sparse in many, many ways.
If you look at the materials that I'm
going to reference today, a lot of it's
going to be actually pretty old.
It's going to be before the competition from ChatGPT
started to heat up.
So for example, the RLHF paper, learning
to summarize from human feedback,
that's actually incredibly detailed.
I'll point to that today in lecture.
If you're interested, I suggest you
go read some of the appendices.
It contains things like detailed annotation guidelines,
how they were instructing people to give feedback to the models,
similarly with Anthropic's HH paper back in 2022.
And then now that competition has heated up, basically,
none of the vendors want to release
any information about their post-training processes.
The data is very much a trade secret.
And so we are not going to be able to talk about annotation
guidelines and things like that for anything that resembles
a modern language model.
We do have closed source-- or open source models.
But on the other hand, a lot of the open source recipes
rely on distillation.
I think its nature is very different from what the frontier
labs are doing in terms of human data collection, which is really
a very tricky and messy thing.
And I'll try to point out some of that,
but it will be difficult to talk about some
of that very comprehensively.
OK.
And then, just as an example of this,
I was doing some pre-research for this lecture earlier,
and I found this very fun example back in 2023
about the trade secretness of post-training data, where
I guess, Scale AI's internal documents got
leaked at some point.
And they had a whole bunch of very frank conversations
about what was happening in post-training data land.
And one of them was like, well, they
were trying to make Google Bard better,
but they couldn't figure out why GPT-4 was so much better.
And so they said, well, we need to reverse engineer what's
happening, and we need to get our annotators
to produce responses that are more detailed and better
than GPT-4.
So these kinds of competitive dynamics
are happening all the time.
And that's also why some of this detail
is going to be missing from today's lecture.
That said, algorithm-wise, we do have a pretty good handle
on what is happening.
But algorithms are not really the secret sauce.
It's not where a lot of the leverage is.
It's going to be the data.
So if we look at the RLHF papers,
we see a very straightforward recipe, two-part recipe.
The first part is you go and collect some demonstration data.
So for every prompt you want some annotator
to provide supervised fine-tuning data,
so reference responses for that prompt.
And you're going to do some fine-tuning.
Then after you have that, you're going
to do some reinforcement learning of some kind
to try to shape the behavior of the model to be more aligned
or more in line with what humans think are good responses.
So I'm going to start by talking about this very first phase,
which is the SFT part of post-training.
And this is the part that's really basically all about data.
We all know how to SFT a model.
That's basically exactly the same as pre-training.
So the only real difference, with some minor variation,
is going to be the training data.
So I will focus on the training data
almost entirely for this part of the lecture.
OK.
With a little bit of discussion about the method.
So we will go through the data.
We are going to look at some examples.
I'll talk about some historical developments
and what the trends are, at least in open source
post-training data land.
And then I will talk about some pitfalls,
some ways in which collecting this kind of data
is much harder than you think.
And if you've taken classes like 224N,
you're going to find some things that are very reminiscent
of issues that you see when you start building classic
supervised deep learning models from scratch.
So let me take a moment to pause,
and then just talk about the progression of SFT data
over the years.
I think I'm going to go top left to bottom right.
That's roughly my chronological ordering.
And there's been a lot of different tricks
and a lot of things that people have done in the open source
language modeling land to try to both improve system performance
and to try to understand what factors of this kind of data
are useful to train models.
I think, really, the oldest and in some ways
the most visionary of this is things like FLAN.
This was used to train the T5 model by Google.
The rough idea for this was to say, well,
NLP people have already collected
a bunch of supervised data sets of inputs and outputs.
We should just train the model on all of these.
Reasonable thing to try.
Turned out, for various reasons, this
was not the right thing to do.
I'll talk about that later.
Self-instruct, and other follow ups to that, this was also
very forward-looking in terms of its thinking was saying, well,
why can't we use the model itself to generate data?
Well, models are getting better all the time.
And in fact, they might even be better than some
of our annotators.
Why don't we get models to write very good, high quality
responses to our inputs?
And that's the self-instruct idea.
And then there came a bunch of distillation style approaches.
Alpaca is one of them.
The Berkeley folks had one called
Vicuna in which they were using online user shared
prompts as the way to-- as the inputs to distill on.
And then there were other efforts
that were more entirely human-driven, like Open Assistant.
You can think of this kind of like Wikipedia.
It was a bunch of people getting together
to write prompts and responses.
And then you have a new generation WizardLM
and Tulu3 and others of saying, well,
that language models are very good synthetic data generators.
Why don't we come up with increasingly complicated ways
of generating instruction following
data using language models?
And then finally, I'll touch briefly on this.
SFT and post-training has changed yet again in recent years because I think the focus is less on chat,
and much more on agents and tool use.
And so there is now a new generation of SFT pipelines
that are designed to generate tool use and agentic data.
So this is roughly a bunch of different developments
in post-training data land, at least in the open source world.
So in the closed source world, where--
well, some of the companies may be distilling each other,
but where you're also collecting human data.
How you're collecting the human data
is a big important ingredient.
That's not reflected in any of this discussion.
OK.
I can pause here in case anyone has questions
before I move on to what we're going
to do next is look at some of the details of these data sets.
Good.
Oh, yeah.
So for post-training, we need the input-output pairs, right?
That's right.
So input-output pairs.
Does the correctness of those input-output pairs matter?
How far does it--Yeah.
So the question was how much does
the correctness of the input-output pairs matter?
That's a nuanced question.
I mean, I think the top level answer
is you should go collect the highest quality responses you
can because the bad stuff will teach the model to do bad stuff.
On the other hand, it turns out that you can SFT models
on all sorts of strange things, and they will
learn to follow instructions.
I think Percy's former student had a paper in which you're
like training models without even the responses or something.
And you can train models to be instruction following.
And so there's a lot of pre-training generalization
behaviors that let you get away with worse quality data.
So it's actually a pretty nuanced question,
what you need in instruction following data.
OK.
Good.
So I want to maybe start with FLAN.
I think FLAN is very much like a forward-looking data set
for its time.
It's established this idea of doing this multitask
post-training.
If you're going to do downstream tasks,
go collect all the downstream tasks and train on it.
Very reasonable, but smart idea at the time.
But if we look at what's in FLAN,
we actually find that it's a little bit
of a strange data set.
You have this thing that's like, well, here's an email.
And then there's this thing that gets appended, which
is write a subject line for this email,
and then the subject line goes on the right.
This is a very strange thing.
I don't think you've ever probably prompted
a model to do a task like this, let alone the instructions
at the very end.
And the reason why you get something
like this is because FLAN is generated from existing data
sets.
So there's a data set called Enron emails.
This is basically a way to turn Enron emails
into a supervised task because it has a body, and a subject,
You can make this subject prediction task.
Similarly, you have a summarization task.
This is—I don't know if this was taken from CNN, Daily Mail,
or Exxon, but it was taken from one
of the big, major summarization datasets.
Highlights for this article, take the article part
of a summarization dataset, put the summary on the right.
But you immediately notice, compared
to something like ChatGPT, the summaries are very short.
In fact, if you look really closely,
the summaries are often hallucinated.
There's a bunch of details that are not in the inputs.
And in some ways, related to this question,
the original NLP datasets, from which FLAN was built,
was not the highest of quality.
And so when you train on this thing,
you also inherit a whole bunch of deficiencies from those data
sets.
And the unnaturalness of the structure of these data
sets also carry down all the way.
And so this is a very smart idea.
FLAN is a very smart idea to create this big dataset out
of these dataset—existing benchmarks.
But really, the unnaturalness really gets you.
And I'll mention one more thing, going back one slide.
I think when FLAN was originally constructed,
part of the theory of how post-training should work
was that you needed scale.
In pre-training, we know we need a lot of scale.
So you might also think that in post-training, we
need a ton of scale to unlock capabilities.
And so because of that, they took tons of datasets and lots
of data, and had this gigantic dataset.
We'll see later on that a lot of these datasets
just get really much smaller, and it still works.
And so really, part of the change from FLAN to later data
sets is this observation that if you have a sufficiently strong,
big, pre-trained model, you can actually get away
with very few high quality examples because
of pre-training generalization is going to get you
quite a bit of the way.
And so it's the wrong point in some ways on the quality,
quantity trade-off.
Although, there was no way to until we explored the full space
of these data sets.
And then I think, after that, maybe next point in how
instruction tuning data sets are understanding of it changed
was after ChatGPT came out, some of my students
did this thing called Alpaca, where
they distilled ChatGPT traces to get input-output pairs.
So this is an example from that data set.
You get more natural-looking inputs, longer chatty outputs.
Because of course, it's taken from ChatGPT.
And what we found was that these kinds of examples, now,
reliably induced ChatGPT-like behavior on models.
Importantly, only when we did it to the original Llama models,
so pre-training, post-training, both of them need to work out.
But we did find that this was the point at which
these things started to work.
And so I think people realized at this point
that if you got this kind of chat-style data,
it was actually not that hard to build ChatGPT-style systems.
Getting the details right is still hard,
but to get most of the way.
So then I think there was this big push to create, essentially,
the highest quality human-driven version of these kinds of data
sets.
To give you a little bit more context, at the time,
I think after ChatGPT came out and Alpaca came out,
I think there was this enormous optimism
that if only we could collect a sufficiently high quality
and large, instruction-tuning data set,
we could then catch up and match a lot
of the performance of these big closed source labs.
So there's a lot of energy and excitement
to building these data sets.
And so in that context, Open Assistant
is this big crowdsourced effort to build such a data set.
So a lot of volunteers got together
and they said, well, we're going to come up with really
hard and interesting prompts.
We're going to come up with good, high quality responses,
and we're going to do it at scale.
In the same way that Wikipedia managed
to produce something very high quality at scale.
A very admirable, very impressive effort
that generated actually a decent amount of data.
I forget if it's like 10,000 or more examples before stalling
out as a project.
I can maybe talk about that if someone's interested.
But if you look now, we have chat-style inputs, very long,
detailed, high quality expert responses on the right.
Good stuff.
I'll talk about some of the pitfalls later as well.
OK.
Finally, I've taken this from some
of the newest of the instruction-tuning data sets.
We've really started to move as a field,
or in terms of the products that people want,
from just a chat interface to something that's
like a full agent system.
So we don't want just textual responses.
We want tool calls.
We want to-do lists.
If you've ever used Cloud Code or Codex,
you know that it produces a to-do list
to check off as it goes.
We want all of those things.
And so SFT data now, if you look at, for example
Nemotron, so that's NVIDIA's open source efforts,
their SFT data, a big chunk of it
is these kinds of agentic SFT examples,
where not only do you have the responses, which are provided
in the assistant field here, but also tool calls that can happen
in parallel alongside the text.
And this is SFT data.
So this is explicitly supervised into the model.
And so now, we're moving much more
towards these structured formats.
And I've been talking about this as I've gone through.
But we've seen big, higher level transitions
in how we think about and build these kinds of data sets.
It's useful to roughly internalize these perspectives.
One of them is this chattiness thing.
It's hard for me to fully articulate what this is,
but there is a sense in which the classic NLP data sets, even
the high quality ones, were very input to programmatic output
almost.
But people don't really want to talk to NLP benchmark,
they want to talk to people.
And so there was this big shift that
has happened towards more detailed human-like responses.
There's a big shift towards higher quality annotators,
and much more detailed.
Open Assistant is a good example of this, of having
experts write your responses.
And then finally, tool use and figuring out the right interface
and API for all of this has been a big final shift
that's been happening.
I'm sure things will keep changing,
but these are some high level factors
to think about in terms of how SFT data has changed
over the last few years.
OK.
I'll talk about all sorts of pitfalls or challenges
in a moment.
Any questions on the specifics of data sets and things
like this?
Good.
OK.
So now, I think, let's say, you are
put in charge of collecting human annotation data for SFT.
What kinds of things should you be mindful of?
There's lots of formatting things
that you might want to think about.
There's also things like knowledge,
how much knowledge should be put into the responses?
How much data points do you want?
And how do you deal with safety of your model?
What kinds of safety data should you be collecting?
And I think one thing I want to highlight is length is--
and style variation, in general, is a very, very big part
of this post-training process.
People say, Claude has a different tone than ChatGPT.
ChatGPT is too chatty, so on and so forth.
All of these are conscious decisions
that are made by the data collection folks.
And also, we see very wide variation
if you look at the data sets in terms
of the length of the responses.
And one thing I do want to highlight
is when you go and evaluate preferences,
these stylistic factors matter a ton.
So people will get very easily tricked.
I don't know if tricked is the right word.
They will very often select responses
that have bullet-pointed lists in their outputs,
or they will select responses that
have more and longer detail.
I think part of this is very natural, especially
if you're in an evaluation setting, where you put in front
of two examples and someone asks you which one is better,
I think more detailed and list-like responses
are generally good.
But this does induce very explicit distortions
in the kinds of tone that a chatbot has relative to people.
These factors-- oh, yeah.
So [INAUDIBLE] complex matter in the data set?
I'll talk about that later.
And you can ask me questions if I don't fully
answer your question then.
But I think the thing about style,
and the thing to be careful about,
is if you're looking at engagement signals,
as most of these companies are, it's very, very easy
to fool yourself into thinking you're getting better data,
when in reality, your model's capabilities are not changing.
So if you look at all of these different kinds
of post-training data sets that you can train on,
you'll see big variations in preferences when you
train on some of these things.
So that's the right column over there, AlpacaEval, for example.
But really, it doesn't necessarily
change standard benchmarking evaluations.
So your models aren't necessarily smarter
because you've trained on certain kinds
of post-training data, at least in these ones.
But you can very much shift the engagement signals.
And so this is telling you, you want
to think about style control separately
from capabilities control.
OK.
The other thing, and this, I think,
is a quite, in many ways, important thing
to think about in terms of how we collect and think
about post-training data.
I think Open Assistant is very instructive
because it was an effort that was intended
to be the highest quality in some ways, post-training data.
And so you often see things like this.
Like for example, this reference-- sorry,
this response contains a reference to an article.
This J Michel, the pay of corporate executives, and blah, blah.
And so this is actually teaching the model two different things
at once.
Let's say, you're SFT-ing on this data.
So first of all, you're doing next token prediction.
So it's teaching the model about this Bivens J & Michelle L
citation.
It's also telling the model another thing, which
is when you're giving a response, a good thing to do
is to give a reference.
So these are two different mechanisms
that are going on at once.
You're teaching the model about different pieces of knowledge,
which is good because you want the model to be knowledgeable,
but you're also teaching the model
to emit detailed knowledge.
And this is sometimes problematic
because what this is going to force the model to do
is sometimes it will misgeneralize,
and it will hallucinate out a reference instead of actually
giving a proper reference.
Models don't really know necessarily
whether a reference is true or false.
And there's been a lot of interesting arguments
that people have made around this.
And I think the folklore, which I think is not wrong.
There's some good empirical evidence
to support this folklore.
Is that if you train a model, especially at the SFT phase,
to emit facts that it does not, this will make it hallucinate.
Because the model, as I said, is trying
to generalize two behaviors at once.
It's trying to generalize the knowledge but also the format.
And so teaching it something where
you have the format in a piece of unknown knowledge
is kind of teaching the model to forcibly emit unknown knowledge.
And people have shown that if you train on, for example,
information that you don't really know,
then this leads to hallucination and overfitting
to pieces of knowledge.
Whereas if you're training on only known facts,
you don't necessarily see this.
John Schulman makes a separate argument,
which is that this is the reason why you need reinforcement
learning and training.
I mean, this is unsurprising because if you
know John Schulman, he's like a reinforcement learning guy.
He made PPO.
Of course, he is very pro reinforcement learning.
But the argument is sound.
That, in some ways, in order to teach
the model what it knows and doesn't
do have to be policy-dependent.
You can't have an external person shoving knowledge down
your throat if you want the model to be calibrated about
what it knows and doesn't.
OK.
And so to put that piece together,
you might not want to train on the highest quality data
if the model doesn't already have that data.
Tail knowledge can actually sometimes
be actively harmful in that it might induce hallucinations,
especially if it's associated with markers
like reference colon.
They'll force the model to emit a reference afterwards.
I'll talk about RLHF later, but this is one of the reasons why reinforcement learning is
important and useful.
For things that are model-dependent,
knowing what you know, RL is a very useful way
to teach models to not say things that it does not know.
And so knowledge storage is actually
very messy and a very nuanced concept.
You don't really want to just say yes, just pack
knowledge in there.
You want to be very careful about exactly what supervision
you're throwing in at the post-training stage.
This is one of the reasons why I think
post-training is quite messy.
You have to deal with all of these realities of serving
a system eventually to a user.
Yes.
What's the definition of tail knowledge?
Yeah.
I don't think there's a formal definition of knowledge.
For example, in the past when I've worked on things like this,
it's been things like the number of times
that-- sorry, the length of a Wikipedia article, for example,
might be a proxy for its well-knownness.
And then you might say, yes, if we
train on stuff that's not well known,
we do see that the model hallucinates more.
But there's no formal like, yes, this is tail
and this is not knowledge, because knowledge
itself can't really be pinned down, precisely.
OK.
Yeah.
The question was why would RL help for hallucinations?
And the reason why RL might help,
let me give a folk story for why this might help.
Imagine, the model has internal to it.
I know something direction inside its activations.
SFT time, maybe what's happening is
you forced it to generate references from your SFT data.
And so it's just going to generate references no matter what.
But when you RL, you might notice
that you get good rewards when you generate references in the I
know stuff direction.
And you get bad rewards when you generate references in the I
don't know direction.
And so then you might then learn to generalize that I know things
or don't things activations into whether you emit a reference.
So it's possible that if you know what
somewhere inside the model, RL can help you extract that
into your output policy.
If you don't know what you know at all, at any level,
RL cannot help you there.
It can't help you with the problem of having
some level of calibration.
Yeah.
So just to follow up on that.
But if it emitted a bad reference,
where do you get penalized in the loss function?
In SFT, well, in some ways, implicitly, you're
getting penalized for anything that is not a reference,
like assigning any probability mass to something
that is not this exact sequence is penalized.
So in some ways, SFT isn't doing the wrong thing.
This is a correct sequence.
The problem is SFT is the generalization properties of this.
That I can't perfectly generalize off this one example.
There's two things, two disentangled things that
are being taught here, one is the reference template,
and then the other thing is the actual content of the knowledge.
And if I generalize based on the template, I'm in big trouble.
Great.
Great questions.
Yeah.
OK.
另外我想谈的是安全性。
一旦我们完成预训练，我们
就必须真正开始面对
人们将如何使用它的种种复杂现实。
我认为预训练的人生活在象牙塔里，
就像让我们压缩整个世界。
但后训练的人必须说，是的。
但如果人们在使用我们的系统
进行政治操纵和虚假信息传播呢？
后训练的人可能会说，是的，
我们看到了 individualized spearfishing。
我们需要防止这种情况发生。
在某些方面，你是最后一道防线，
在你和系统被滥用之间。
那么你该怎么做？
嗯，你必须对系统施加安全控制。
它会拒绝对恶意输入作出回应。
这是这些公司实际采用的
执行安全控制的方式。
所以这就落在了后训练团队的肩上。
不幸的是，安全 SFT 信息
似乎比能力相关的
SFT 信息在公开文件中更为稀少。
我提取了 Llama 2 的描述，
关于他们如何做安全 SFT。
如果说有什么不同，这是较为详细的描述之一。
但你会看到他们甚至
没有谈到用了多少示例。
他们用于安全调优，这在我看来有点疯狂。
但无论如何，实际上，所有
安全调优方法运作的框架
都是要平衡两件事。
你想平衡我允许多少
坏查询通过，我认为这就是违规
率。
然后你也不想过度拒绝，
因为有人可能会问这样的问题，
我如何杀死一个 Python 进程。
然后如果你是一个机器人，它就会说，不，
I can't let you kill anything, that's
very frustrating to the user.
And so the false refusal rate also needs to be low.
So you want to control this and have a good Pareto
trade-off between the two.
And so what you do is you basically create
various kinds of tailored data to navigate this trade-off.
In terms of the scale of the amount of data
you collect, you usually have something like a few thousand
or tens of thousands of examples.
For example, in Llama 2, I think it's
about a few thousand examples that are used for this process.
This state of affairs is a little bit
unsatisfying if I left you with only that slide.
So I will talk about it in a little bit more detail.
I think if you want to look at how post-training is done,
maybe the only good reference right now would be two or three.
This would be the post-training pipeline for the OLMo models
that Allen AI put out.
And given the lack of details about post-training
in many places, this is one of the few places where
you can see a reasonably performant
post-training pipeline in action.
And they do have, for example, a safety component,
which consists of something like 50,000-ish examples total.
And if you look, they all follow the same fairly simple strategy
for generating SFT data, which is the following.
In a previous project, they had this thing
called WildChat, where basically they gave free API or free chat
access to a bunch of people so that they
can go out and use various kinds of chat interactions.
In exchange, they collected what they were doing on those chats.
And from that, they were able to basically filter out
a whole bunch of unsafe behaviors that were being attempted
to be done on these chat interfaces,
as well as jailbreaks that people attempted to do.
And so they mined these at scale,
and then created essentially the preferred response,
which is to resist the jailbreak in one case,
and to say no in another case.
Fairly, very straightforward approach.
And I think from what we see, at least in the technical reports
and the model cards of the various closed source companies,
similar things are happening, and that you
look at your usage information, you find unsafe behaviors.
You get your annotators to play whack-a-mole
with these bad behaviors.
OK.
The final thing I'll mention, and this related to what I said about the number of examples
that you need for SFT.
I think one thing, if you haven't played with SFT before
that you will be surprised by, is
if you have a sufficiently capable model,
it does not take very many examples to steer these systems.
So if you want to do something safety tuning,
if you take 500 examples, let's say,
in the vein of you find a bunch of unsafe stuff,
or you synthesize a bunch of unsafe stuff,
and then you write refusals and you put that into the system,
you'll find that even with as little as 500 examples, the rate
at which you follow malicious instructions or other kinds
of hate speech instructions, and so on, drops dramatically.
And with 500 examples, you're really
applying this fairly surgical--
not surgical, very small push to the model.
But that results in a fairly nice across the board
reduction in these safety issues over here.
And so one way to think about it is models
already have am I going to be a safe model
or an unsafe model access inside of it after pre-training
so it does not take very many examples to pull this out.
Now, one thing to also remember at the end of this just because you can steer a model
with very few examples, doesn't mean that there's
no benefit to more examples.
If you're OpenAI or Anthropic, and you
want to enforce really fine grained distinctions about what
is safe and not safe, you do need very large scale data
collection does.
This doesn't really change that story.
OK.
So SFT at its best is this thing where
if you're extracting pre-training behaviors,
like it's already in there somewhere in pre-training,
and all you want to do is pull out the right modes out
of the model, then instruction fine tuning works very, very
well.
With very little data, as long as you
have the right high quality ones,
you can get the model to do what you want.
And adding data or factually correct ones
can sometimes hurt you, at least in terms of hallucination.
And then finally, it doesn't take very much data.
And so you can often focus on quality instead of quantity.
Good.
OK.
This is going to be the end of the data part for SFT.
So if anyone has questions, ask me before I move on.
Yes.
How do we know what is already a behavior [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
The question was how do we whether something
is in pre-training?
I think this is the sloppiness of what I was saying,
which is that we don't really know per se.
We can know what things aren't in pre-training.
We can look for the kinds of generalization to, for example,
programming languages that are very rare that's
very hard using SFT.
So we can show those things.
We can't show necessarily that, for example, safety is something
that's in pre-training per se.
Yes.
Can you talk more about this when you talk about RL.
But there's this whole question of SFT destroying features
with RL invading them.
That's like [INAUDIBLE] trying to talk about that.
I'm not going to talk about that later.
The question was whether SFT is destroying features in RLs
like pushing up or down.
I think the lines are very blurry between the two,
To be honest, especially when we get into something
like expert iteration and all these other things, that
look like SFT with extra bells and whistles.
So I don't necessarily think it's
a core distinction between RL and SFT,
rather that it's more of a distinction in the kinds
of feedback that we get.
SFT is this dense feature supervision,
whereas RL is the self-taught policy supervision.
And the other thing about RL is that you're
getting your own output from your own policy.
So there's a sense in which you don't maybe
deviate quite as far in what you're being reinforced on.
And that's probably an important part of what's happening.
So now, let's talk about methods.
For most of this class, we've been
excited to talk about methods.
In this part, it is about the most boring thing
because you just do gradient descent.
I just put the picture here as almost a joke.
You just take loss.backwards and that's basically it.
But there is one nuance I do want
to talk about that is important, which
is this increasing trend of turning instruction tuning
into part of pre-training.
It used to be that when these things first appeared,
the pre-training and post-training were
just these separate ideas, that you would pre-train on web data,
and then you would post-train afterwards.
But people realized why separate two things when
you can mix them together.
And so lots of high quality data, and even
instruction tuning data, is now getting
mixed in at the tail end of training
when the decay phase usually of training happens.
And this really allows you to scale up instruction tuning.
It also allows you to essentially emphasize
higher quality data.
The impact of this has been quite dramatic.
And so everyone, as far as I know, is doing it.
You can see it in most of the model release reports,
that there's a mid training or a second phase pre-training
with a different data mix.
And importantly, one thing that I'll-- this is my pet peeve.
I'll say is that now, when someone tells you
something is a base model, that's kind of a lie.
Because a base model is usually about, yes,
predicting the next word on internet data or something.
Well, really, base models today are pre-trained on Ultra Chat,
and who knows what else.
Those are like chat data sets that are synthetically designed
to make you good at chat.
And so it's very hard to say that this is like a base model in the traditional sense of the word.
I've taken this example of a two-phase training.
I think this one's from MiniCPM.
Because I think they show very nicely the change in the mix.
So this first bar is the very standard pre-training phase,
where you've got all sorts of internet data on the left.
And on the right, you're kind of switching
to this higher quality, and also very chatty data set.
You've got Stack Exchange QA.
You've got Ultra Chat.
You've got all sorts of other SFT data.
And then you've decreased the fraction
of standard general purpose pre-training data.
So almost everyone does this today.
And you can think of the point of this
as saying, well, the boundaries between pre-training
and instruction tuning, and also high quality data is just
being blurred very much.
Yes.
Are the queries masked in this kind of data?
No, this is pure pre-training.
And so you're also predicting the prompt as well.
But actually, that's not a huge difference
because some SFT recipes do also predict the prompt.
Yes.
So the question was whether the data quality
is lower in the decay.
Usually, the intuition is you want
the reverse, that the decay is the most important part
of your training.
It's the part that's closest to deployment during pre-training.
Also, it's the part with the lowest learning rate.
And so for both of those reasons, maybe
you want to put the highest quality stuff into the decay.
And so I guess, Book Chinese, and all these things
are supposed to be higher quality.
Certainly, Wiki and Stack Exchange
is usually considered high quality.
Yes.
How is the mixture--
I guess, for pre-training, you discussed other mixtures
beside these [INAUDIBLE] cheaper models.
And then from there, you can use statistical analysis to decide.
But then, I guess, for midtraining and post-training,
you have to essentially run it on the larger model,
or do people still have some smaller model
they use as a proxy?
I assume there's some reduction in the amount of information
you can build.
I guess, you mentioned what's good there
about these data mixtures and where do they get them.
Yeah.
So data mixtures, I mean, both for pre-training
and post-training are very trial and error.
We do have algorithms like many people have written papers
about things in this space.
But I think they're fairly unreliable.
There's a lot of trial and error and intuition
that happens for this space.
But the nice thing about this two-phase training
and this midtraining stuff is that midtraining is much shorter
than full pre-training.
So if you're doing data mix optimization for midtraining,
you can run something like 10 of these for each one of these
on the left, right.
And so this lets you not quite brute force the problem,
but it does let you try a lot of ablations.
And so actually, I think the usual way that I've
heard a lot of this done is actually in the decay phase,
you do a lot of data ablations, which
are cheap to run and so on, and then you
get estimates of data quality and then you reflect that
even back to the first stage—into the pre-training.
Into the pre-training stage.
Yeah.
So to decide the pre-training mix,
often, you actually run a bunch of ablations on decay.
And then you will figure out what to put back
or how to set the pre-training mix.
The reason why you don't just make pre-training high quality
is you just don't have enough tokens.
You'll run out of tokens if you try to make Wikipedia
your whole pretrained.
Is there any intuition based on the information you get from,
I guess, how good the [INAUDIBLE] performance was
with your prior mixture.
Is there any intuition with how those are—
how it's adjusted, I guess?
That's very case by case of how you
go from downstream deltas on ablations to mixes.
There are systematic ways you can
fit models and do these things, but they're often brittle.
What I've heard from people is that actually, it's
much more trial and error than you think.
You ablate a domain, you make rankings
over which ablations had the most impact,
and then you decide what to put in.
Actually, a good example of this, a fun example
of this, that's been leaked is when
Meta got sued for using Books.
In the court documents, there's actually
a bunch of documents showing some researchers
doing ablations and trying to estimate,
how useful are each of these Book subsets.
And so that's exactly the kinds of things that happen.
And then ultimately, they'll decide based
on that what the mixes are.
Cool.
OK.
So now, we're done with SFT.
The algorithm part was very short.
And now we get to talk about RLHF.
So this is the second phase.
We're done with doing supervised fine tuning.
Now, we're going to do something very
different from pre-training, where we're just
going to upweight or downweight different model outputs based
on how a rater, or in some cases, a reward
model decides how good these responses are.
And before we get into algorithms and stuff,
I do want to pause for one moment on this slide
and talk about a conceptual difference
that I think is actually quite important.
Maybe it's less important for people
that weren't originally coming from StatML background
and so on.
But I think there is actually a very different way
of thinking about SFT or even pre-training and RLHF.
So in pre-training, what are we doing?
We're doing generative modeling of some sequence.
So you have a collection of sequences
and you're trying to predict the next word.
SFT is also the same.
You've changed the distribution, but you're
predicting the next word.
So you can think about this using your generative modeling
brain.
This is purely a generative modeling problem.
And then you're just going to fit some distribution.
Now once we get to the second part, the RLHF,
we are no longer playing a fit a distribution game.
We are fitting a maximize a reward game.
So what we want is we want to find some distribution.
We still have a distribution.
This is a policy now.
Such that this policy is going to maximize
some downstream reward.
And maybe that reward is something like how long your users
are engaged on your platform.
Maybe that reward is like what math problems you can solve,
but there's some reward.
And I don't care if I've mimicked some distribution.
And this is conceptually very different
because now, in the second world,
I can totally collapse out my distribution onto a single point
for every input.
So for every prompt, my model could have a single answer, not
a distribution.
And that would be OK, as long as it got a good reward.
So that's a big important conceptual distinction
to keep in your mind.
And I wanted to highlight it before we get
into some of the later bits.
OK.
So now, why do we want to do this thing of doing
reinforcement learning?
We could just say, why don't you forever go and collect SFT data?
Well, I think one thing that is important for thinking about RL
is when we try to optimize what humans want,
there is sometimes a big difference in what they say they
want and what they generate.
And that's one thing that we found in the past study.
I put this here because I find this so funny,
even though it's a little bit old now.
We asked a bunch of freelance writers
to summarize news documents.
And we found that a few annotators actually
preferred Instruct Davinci, which
was the predecessor to ChatGPT, over their own writing.
And that was very strange.
And we were like, are these guys actually doing annotation?
So we interviewed them, and we asked
them like, why did you like the AI
outputs over your own writing?
And they said, well, I looked at it
and I thought, actually, this is pretty good stuff.
And so it turned out that, they're writers, they're good,
they're good at writing.
Their summaries are high quality.
We check it for quality.
But actually, when they looked at it,
they were like, I didn't realize that's actually
a better way of doing it.
So people aren't really these optimal systems.
And so when they judge things, it's actually different.
And so because of this gap, sometimes
you might want to rate outputs rather than just
to generate demonstrations.
Another reason is that in some domains,
verification is a lot easier than generation.
Math, which I'll talk about more next lecture,
is a prime example of this, where verifying a proof
is probably much easier than generating the proof.
And folks like DeepSeek have gone down
that path for self-verification using models.
That's another place, where this idea
of having reinforcement learning and judging yourself
is a good idea.
OK.
I'm not going to cover what people call RLVR today.
That's its own universe.
It's going to be an entire lecture next time.
I'll talk about the exciting promises of reasoning models.
But today, I'm going to talk about RLHF.
In RLHF, we'll have different components.
And I'm going to talk about data, how do we collect it.
And then I'm going to talk about algorithms,
how do we actually do it.
And I'll talk about two major families of algorithms
before talking about maybe some pitfalls at the very end.
OK.
Good.
So in RLHF, the high level way that we do things is now we
have a good model after SFT.
It follows some instructions.
We now put prompts into the model.
The model is going to generate a couple of different outputs.
And we usually do this by just sampling with temperature one.
At the end of SFT, the model is pretty diverse,
so this is a reasonable thing to do.
A rater comes in and rates all of the examples
and provides a ranking over the examples.
Sometimes, even a binary ranking.
And then a model is going to be trained on those rankings.
And we're going to use standard reinforcement learning
techniques to maximize the score that we get on that reward
model.
And we go through the reward model
because it might be easier to train a verifier
than to train a model that does well directly.
OK.
So how do we get data for this thing?
As I said before, the general way in which we do this is to get pairwise ratings.
And so you're going to have an interface like this, where
you have a couple AI responses and you're
going to give a response saying response one or two is better.
This is just a standard annotation interface
that I've gone and found, but most places have similar things.
We can now look at what an actual company would do in order
to do this.
It's not that different, although they have some nuances.
If you want to go and really read up on this,
I would suggest you look at the InstructGPT appendix.
It's the last point at which we have a glimpse
into data collection processes from industry.
And so at least in the InstructGPT case, they say,
OK, we want you to rate these outputs
for being helpful, truthful, and harmless.
So they have to balance three things.
Helpfulness is how clear the writing is,
or being sensitive to internationality,
or not giving overly long answers.
You want to be truthful, so don't hallucinate.
And then harmless, if it's unsafe,
we want you to say that-- or we want
you to upweight things that are refusing to respond
to questionable prompts.
So this makes sense as an omnibus objective
for training chatbots.
Another very similar example that I found
is, this is, I think, the only other example of a closed source
lab annotation being out in the public.
This one is for Google Bard.
So that was quite a while ago, but their annotations
got leaked by some annotators.
And you can see they have a very similar structure
of saying, we want helpfulness, we want the presentation
of the response to be good.
And actually, their rating is a Likert scale
rather than pairwise feedback, but they
have a very similar structure.
It's not a very super long set of instructions,
but you get the sense what kinds of things are included,
like don't contain inaccurate information
or be coherent and be easy to consume, so short for the user
to read.
Things have changed quite a bit since then.
There are a couple of different surveys of annotators.
I think the high level thing that I'll
say before going through the next two slides
is, in general, I think the worker
distribution for annotation has shifted
upwards, more towards experts, more towards higher cost.
And we see that in compensation and things like this.
So if you look at the education level of data annotators,
this is for one of ScaleAI's platforms.
So it's not representative of the full space of data
annotators for language models.
But this is probably a reasonable subset of those.
The majority, or a large fraction of them,
are bachelor's degrees or master's holders.
So that's like 70% of these annotators.
And the age is something like 35 is the modal age.
And the task that they're doing are
often like creative writing and technical writing and so on,
are often the tasks that these annotators end up performing.
This is one step towards experts, but I think even more,
there's been a growth in the last year or two
in bespoke annotators.
And I think this is because a lot of the labs
are now pushing into deploying these systems
in actual white collar jobs.
And so you want doctors, you want lawyers,
you want these people to annotate the responses.
You want them to give SFT data.
And so there are these projects that
are internal to these companies like OpenAI,
where annotators are being paid a pretty decent wage per hour
to do these annotations.
And so if you look at the median wages,
they're above $50 across a range of different topics.
But if you look at the experts, some of these experts
are being paid more than $100 per hour to do annotation work.
And so I think this is to say, if your mental model
of an annotator was low cost pairwise feedback
from somewhere overseas, that's not really the full picture.
There's a lot of annotation happening right now that's
very bespoke, very expensive, but it's kind of also a pyramid.
It's not like that lower cost scalable
annotation has gone away.
OK.
And to emphasize this point to you, getting this kind of data
is actually very challenging.
That's why the pay is high.
That's why there's so many data collection startups.
I think the hard challenges now is
getting verifiable annotators, especially ones where you're
sure that they're not using AI.
If you all have done survey research, or crowdsourcing
recently, I'm sure you found that people are using ChatGPT
as part of their survey responses
or as part of their annotation workloads.
Basically, preventing people from doing
this is extremely, extremely difficult. It's
also very difficult to get truly correct responses
when people are under time pressure.
For example, that Google Bard example
that was part of, I think, some labor dispute where
the annotators for Google Bard were saying,
we have to check the correctness of these long chat responses
in under a minute.
It's impossible for us to do that.
There's no way that we can actually
follow these instructions.
And to add, there's a growing amount of expert data
collection, but there's also a very large amount, still,
of low paid annotation groups.
ScaleAI, I think, did quite a bit of this initially.
I don't know if they still do, where
they outsourced a lot of this low cost annotation
and got into quite a bit of trouble.
And so in the same way that I guess the modern economy has
this bifurcation in terms of high and low wage jobs,
we see the same thing with annotations as well.
The final thing I want to talk about in terms of annotators
is demographics.
One thing that's quite important is
that annotators have a surprising amount of influence
over what the model does.
So post-training comes at the end.
And it's, in some sense, the final shaping step of the model
before it gets shipped out.
So if you're not really precise with how the annotators steer
the model, and your annotation groups have biases,
you can actually end up getting some pretty surprising behavior.
So one of the studies that we did
in the early days of instruction tuning
with one of my postdocs, between Percy and I,
was that we looked at essentially
which kinds of ideological opinions
language models were more aligned to.
And we did this by asking standard opinion poll questions
to language models, and seeing which human demographics they
were closest to.
And so what you find-- or what we found
is that base models of various kinds
were kind of similar to Protestants or Roman Catholic
opinions, and far from Buddhist or Hindu ones.
And then what we found is that if you post-train
these models, so the three right columns,
you find that they're more different from Protestants
and Roman Catholics, and become more similar to Buddhist,
Hindus, and atheists in terms of the kinds of opinions
that they give.
And we're like, that's really strange.
Why these three groups?
It turns out, if you look at the appendix of the InstructGPT
paper, you find the annotators, who
were annotating for these models,
and they line up, like a lot of Southeast Asians,
and also people in the West Coast of America.
And that's roughly the demographic groups corresponding
to these.
You also find, I guess, another added note in the recent years,
there's been a lot of findings that very subtle biases
can transmit through data.
So one example of this is something
called emergent misalignment.
If you have a piece of data trained from a model
or generated from a model, that's been trained to say like,
I like owls or something, and you train on
that innocuous looking data, the model trained on it
will actually inherit a preference for owls.
And so there's all these weird kinds of subliminal transfer
effects that can happen with data
that are quite hard to catch.
And so that's one thing to be really,
really quite careful about.
And this is true, more generally.
I think this whole study of LLM political opinions
and so on can be quite fragile and sketchy at times.
But the annotator distribution and who your annotators are also
matters quite a bit for the different kinds more
material errors that your model might make.
So this is a study that's quite nice by Hosking, et al,
where they studied like if I get really
expert annotators, like people who really care about doing
the job right, versus random collection of crowdworkers,
how do their annotations differ?
And they show very nice, striking results
that people who are just non-expert annotators, that
are just kind of paid on a platform
really like to emphasize formatting effects, which
is this row over here.
You see, it's red.
It's over enriched in these non-expert annotators.
On the other hand, things like factuality or inconsistency
are things that are much more emphasized than the expert
annotators.
Of course, it's much, much harder to test for factuality,
and so it's no surprise that if you don't have experts,
you don't actually end up checking for these.
This is another way in which your distribution of annotators
ends up mattering, not demographic, but here,
how much they care and what their expertise is.
It's been shown for a while now that because of all these-- oh,
was there a question?
Yeah.
I was going to ask how do you measure quality and [INAUDIBLE]?
What are the [INAUDIBLE] to be higher quality than another?
Yeah.
So the question was, what does it mean for one annotator
to be higher quality than another?
I think there's no gold standard rule where you can mechanically
turn the crank and be are a good annotator.
I think, I'll maybe give two different kinds of answers.
One of them is a sufficiently-detailed annotation
guideline should hopefully be semi objective.
You will say, it should be factual.
And then you'll define what factuality is.
And then you might even have objective criteria.
Like in the first three pages of the Google search,
you don't find anything that contradicts it.
And if you can find something that
doesn't follow the guideline, you
can be like, yes, you're not following the rule.
That's one notion of a good annotator.
The other notion of a good annotator
is inter-annotator agreement.
And that's a statement about a population of annotators,
whether they have high variance or not.
I think the only issue with that is it doesn't tell you
what the bias is.
It tells you the variance.
And some tasks inherently have variance.
If you're asking do you like this, that's
a task with lots of variance.
So inter-annotator agreement is not useful.
If you're asking, is it factual, maybe it should be lower.
But even if it's zero, if you've asked the right question.
Or if they're all using ChatGPT, the variance will also be zero.
So it's very hard to assess quality
even though there's ways of maybe getting at that question.
So is the reason you're seeing annotators or companies starting
to recruit more experts, or more educated people
to be annotators because they give somewhat higher quality
or more lower grade on answers?
Or is it because the data that you're collecting
is just something that only these people can answer?
I think it's more of the latter.
Maybe you need a lawyer to check if a Blue Book
annotation is correct.
You need to be relatively well trained to be able to do that.
And there's also tacit knowledge of various kinds
that maybe you want to extract.
So that's one of the reasons.
It is true that I think, in general, the platforms are
moving more towards higher quality annotators,
even for general annotation tasks.
I think a big part of this is because LLMs have gotten good,
and if you don't like in-person supervised people,
they will use the cheapest LLM to generate
plausible-looking answers.
And so I think there's a lot of annotator shops
whose value proposition is basically
like we have real people that do real things,
and we will verify that this is true for you.
Cool.
OK.
Yeah.
What's the largest problem-- and I hear
you might be getting to this.
What's the largest problem using a domain-specific model
as an annotator?
So the question was, what's the problem
with using domain-specific models as an annotator?
I guess there's two separate questions there.
One is like, are domain-specific models good?
And then the other question is like, should we
use models to annotate data?
Model-based data annotation is quite good.
If you're not at the frontier, and what
you want to do is basically catch up to the frontier,
model-based annotation is very, very good.
Modern models are probably much, much better
than random crowd worker you can get.
And so model-based annotations, good idea.
Now, domain-specific models, well,
can you get domain-specific models that are better
than the strongest open models?
Sometimes, quite difficult. And so for that reason,
I don't think there's a unique advantage, for example,
to annotating with domain-specific models.
In general, model-based annotations are a good idea.
OK.
So I didn't plant that question, but we
are moving towards model-based annotations now.
If you look at LLM-generated annotations of various kinds,
you will find that these models are surprisingly good.
When GPT-4 came out, some of my students and I
did comparisons between GPT-4's annotations,
and carefully curated human annotations.
And if you compare the rankings of systems, they're pretty good.
If you compare the agreement between humans
to models, the mode of humans to models, they're pretty good.
And their cost is an order of magnitude less.
所以这一切都很好。
而在当时，当我们最初
在 GPT-4 时代做这件事时，它
仍然不清楚事情会
朝哪个方向发展，比如在开放世界中，
例如，我们会走向昂贵的
人工标注，
还是所有东西都会在某种程度上变成蒸馏，
来自更强的模型。
我想到现在，已经过去足够多年了，
我们知道答案了，那就是基本上
如果你想做的只是
追赶前沿和能力，那么人工收集的数据就没有空间了。
我觉得当时我发现
非常有趣且有启发性的一件事是 Huggingface
当时试图构建一个名为 Zephyr 的开放源代码模型。
而他们当时真正想做的一件事
就是不做任何模型蒸馏。
所以他们说，好吧，我们不会
使用任何基于模型的标注或基于模型的数据，
我们会花费大量时间和精力
收集人类数据。
所以他们去找了 OpenAI 和其他公司
使用的同一批供应商，基本上就是去收集一堆人类数据。
但基本上，他们发现这极其耗时、
昂贵，而且他们得到的结果
实际上并不比使用基于模型的标注更好。
所以最终，他们基本上
就为此使用了基于模型的反馈，
我认为这很有启发性。
他们用自己拥有的资源
非常认真地尝试了。
但最终，他们还是使用了 AI 反馈。
而这基本上一直如此。
所以对于 SFT，以及对于 RLHF，我们
发现 UltraChat 和 UltraFeedback，
这些由模型生成的，现在非常标准。
Tulu3，我提到过它是大型的、几乎是
旗舰级的开放源代码后训练流程之一，
其整个流程都使用基于模型的标注。
And so this is basically where we've
ended up in terms of should we use
model-based annotations or not.
Models are very good at following instructions,
very scalable.
So you can collect the right kinds of data that you want.
And this is roughly where things are.
Of course, if you want to push the frontier out,
you don't get to necessarily play
these games, except in limited circumstances.
And so you're still very much reliant on human-driven data
collection.
OK.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] example.
What is the [INAUDIBLE] model [INAUDIBLE]
because 7B is [INAUDIBLE] very small.
Well, 7B is small now.
I guess, at the time, I guess, 7B
was a very respectable open source model.
It's like Llama is a 7B.
Everyone loves Llama 7B.
We too would like to train a 7B.
And so in that sense, it was respectable.
I don't know if they went and tried it for their bigger runs,
but at least, at that scale, they
weren't seeing any differences.
I would be very surprised if they switched to the bigger one,
and suddenly there was a big difference.
Cool.
OK.
There are other places where you might do model generation that
is not purely distillation.
Anthropic had an early work on self-training.
This was Constitutional AI, where they kind of prompted
a model to generate safety data, and then
they trained the model itself on that prompted data.
And that allowed them to get a safer model out of the model.
And you can think of this as a very early self post-training
data generation loop.
And the other paper-- sorry, the other project
that I mentioned to you of a self-instruct, that's
a different kind of capability-centric version
of this kind of idea.
So you can use models to bootstrap
your own post-training data.
But if you want something like lawyers or scientists,
you can't get world knowledge without getting people
to annotate.
So you're kind of stuck, at least,
for that, with collecting human annotators.
The other thing I'll mention is that models are also
very susceptible to the same kinds of biases
as humans, sometimes in ways that are quite problematic as
well, even more problematic.
There's been a couple studies, after this kind of wave of model-
generated data, stuff started coming out,
showing that actually you could just push length
of your responses way out.
And you would continue to get improvements
in the win rates of model-judged performance.
And if you look, the one outlier here
is ChatGPT 3.5, basically saying,
well, they're not just length hacking,
they're actually a model that is actually better.
Similarly, others showed-- this was a very nice paper showing
that you can just RLHF on length alone,
and you could do quite well on many of these benchmarks.
So that's roughly the data story.
Who's collecting the data?
What kinds of things to be conscious of?
And then now in the remaining time that I have,
I'm going to talk about the algorithm.
I'm only going to briefly talk about PPO
because both in the interest of time
and because I'm just going to do a more extended treatment next
lecture.
And then I'll talk a little bit about DPO,
which is the cool fun bit.
OK.
So now, remember, we're in the RLHF regime.
The goal is the following.
I'm going to maximize, under my policy, the reward
that I get by sampling from that policy.
And this is like baby reinforcement learning.
Because people might say we're playing bandits.
This is not true multi-turn interesting RL.
And that's roughly right.
And so our algorithms will also be quite simple.
So the objective that I just showed you, maximize reward,
it appears almost exactly in the InstructGPT paper.
If you look at--open the paper up, and you go to equation 2,
you'll find exactly the kind of thing I wrote down,
where you sample from your RL policy,
I want to maximize my reward, subject to this second term,
which is really just a KL divergence.
All that it's saying is I want to stay
close to my pre-trained model because I
don't want to go too far and become degenerate.
Same thing is true from Stiennon, et al.
This is another paper.
You see, the reward in this case is a pairwise feedback model
that you've learned.
So you train a binary classifier on which of a pair of examples
is better.
And then you hill climb on that reward.
So very simple structure that we have.
Now, how do we actually do that hill climbing?
We use an algorithm called PPO.
If you've taken RL class, you, of course, know what PPO is.
If you haven't, I will give you a baby description
of what PPO is.
Also, you'll have to understand it for the assignment.
So the very basic starting point is the policy gradient identity.
What I want to do is I want to maximize my reward
sampling from my policy.
How do I optimize that?
Well, everything in machine learning is gradient descent.
So I take gradients.
So I want the gradient with respect to my parameters.
And you can push the gradient in and do the policy gradient
trick.
And you can show that that's equivalent to the equation on the right.
So I'm just going to take the gradient of my log probabilities
and weigh it by my rewards.
And this really just looks like SFT, but with weighted examples,
effectively.
Now, you might say, OK, policy gradients are great.
I love policy gradients, but the problem with policy gradients
is I need to sample every time I want
to take an optimization step.
And sampling is very expensive.
We've already talked about in the systems parts,
inference is often very complicated and hard,
whereas training is very arithmetically intense and good.
And so I want to roll out once, and I
want to reuse that rollout multiple times.
So this is something called off-policy.
To do off-policy, I want to take multiple steps
but not go too far.
Because if I go too far, my estimates of my local
rewards kind of blow up.
So this is something called TRPO.
The basic idea is I want to take policy gradients,
but I want to stay a little bit close to where
I am while you do something called an importance weighting
correction.
I'm not going to go into that in detail.
Finally, PPO says, well, TRPO is a good idea,
but this distance constraint is actually
kind of hard to deal with.
And so I'm going to come up with a heuristic clipping
thing that's just going to discourage the RL
algorithm from going to places where I'm too
far from the original policy.
I'll go through the details of this in the next lecture.
So you don't need to worry about it.
But the main progression of policy
gradient off-policy, you end up at PPO.
Hopefully, you roughly understand.
PPO，其实，这些公式看起来有点复杂。
所以很多人很多年来
都在问下面这个问题。
我们能去掉PPO吗？
这对很多人来说是一件大事。
很多有道理的人思考过
很多去掉PPO的好方法。
我会把它们告诉你，这样你就不一定
在自己的研究中重复它们。
例如，你可以说，我有一对例子，
我可以做SFT，但是用一种特殊的SFT。
对于好的那个例子，我会在前面加一个好token。
对于坏的那个例子，我
会在前面加一个坏token。
所以你会附加一些token。
然后当我生成时，我就
会在我的回复前面加上good，这样我的模型只会
生成好的内容。
所以这是把PPO简化为SFT，或者把RL简化为SFT。
这行不通。
人们尝试过只用好的内容来训练模型。
效果也不太好。
你可以训练奖励模型，获取LLM输出，
只选择奖励模型选中的内容
并在它们上训练。
这效果也不太好，虽然确实有点用。
所以很多人尝试过，很多不同的迭代。
最终，我们现在确实有了一个东西
比PPO简单得多，效果还不错。
而且在很多方面，看起来就像SFT。
这就是DPO。
所以这个算法非常非常简单。
我们要做的是，我们
要试着去掉PPO中复杂的部分。
我们要去掉什么？
我们要去掉奖励模型。
我们要去掉任何
与on-policy相关的东西。
通过去掉这两样东西，
我们要试着做一个更简单的RLHF算法。
And it relies on a very simple intuition.
Everything in deep learning is just
taking gradient steps in the direction of good things.
And so we're going to take steps in the direction of the log
loss of the good stuff.
And then we will take negative gradient steps
in the direction of the bad stuff.
In other words, we're going to reverse the log probability
of anything that is bad.
This is basically the most naive thing you can do.
Because you're doing SFT on one hand,
and you're doing kind of negative SFT on the bad thing.
It turns out that if you weight these two appropriately,
you will get an algorithm that is actually pretty good.
And I'll give you the derivation because it's all very simple.
So remember, our goal is to optimize this equation over here.
So this should look familiar to you.
The first term is my expected reward under my policy pi theta.
The second term is saying that's my KL distance.
I want my policy to remain close to my reference.
That's what I pretrain.
Now, I'm going to make an assumption.
This is the one strong assumption that I'm going to make.
And I'm going to assume that pi, my policy,
is actually not a neural network at all.
It is the set of all possible policies.
It is a nonparametric thing.
It can approximate anything.
So if pi can be anything, I can actually
solve that top problem closed form.
I actually know what the minimizer is.
And the minimizer is the following.
The minimizer is actually to take my original reference
policy, and to exponentially tilt it by my reward.
In other words, every response gets upweighted or downweighted
with a weight, e to the 1 over beta r
based on how good the reward is.
This makes a lot of sense.
If the reward is really bad, I'm going
to exponentially downweight.
If the reward is really good, I'm
going to exponentially upweight it.
So this is the closed form solution if pi can be anything.
Now, we can then--
now that this pi of r, this perfect solution,
I can solve for the implied reward.
In other words, I can solve for what is
the r that would induce this.
And so I can solve for that.
I can put the pi on the left side,
and I can solve for the reward that we would have.
And then we can take that implied reward that I wrote down.
And then I can solve for what would happen
in the original RLHF objective.
I plug in my reward into that objective here, into my loss.
And this gives the DPO objective, which is very intuitive.
It basically says take gradient steps in the positive direction,
and then take negative gradient steps in the bad direction.
You can already see what's going to happen.
This first term over here, this is the good stuff.
This is the bad stuff on the right term here.
And they're going to be balancing each other.
OK.
And so if I take the gradient of this,
I think this is the most intuitive form of DPO,
at least to me, you have two things.
For every pair that you've had annotated,
I'm going to increase the likelihood of the example,
that one, and I'm going to decrease the likelihood
of the example that lost.
And I'm going to scale the step size in some sense
by how much my implied reward model is wrong.
Did my model already assign a very high reward
to the winning one?
If it did so, I will take a small step.
But if I was very wrong, and I said, oh, these two are almost
equal, I had same probability.
But in that case, I will actually
take a much bigger step size.
So based on the probability differences,
I will take bigger or smaller step sizes on this differential
log prob objective.
So hopefully, the action of this gradient objective
is quite clear to people.
OK.
So this is actually much, much simpler than PPO
because all I'm doing is taking gradients.
And we all know how to do that with our standard processes.
And I think the nice thing is that it does work reasonably
well.
I think for a while, people were very obsessed with, is DPO
better than PPO or vice versa?
I think the answer now is maybe it doesn't matter very much,
unless you're like at the frontier training
the very best model.
DPO is reasonably good.
And it's good enough for LLaMA.
It's good enough for me.
If you go and open up the LLaMA tech report,
you'll find that they basically had this nice outer loop
training, where they had their model, they SFT'd it,
they did DPO.
And then they used that DPO model
to then generate candidates that they rejection sampled and they
repeated this process.
So there's the outer loop on top of it.
But basically, the core RLHF primitive for Llama was DPO.
In the years since, there's been a lot
of different variants of DPO.
There was SimPO, which basically changes the weighting.
So instead of using pi ref, you have this y of l normalizer.
There was length normalized DPO, which normalizes by the length
in order to avoid certain length hacking
issues that seem to arise.
But really, none of these variants
maybe seem to matter very much.
One of the things that I'll mention,
that I thought was very interesting,
was these results are very, very contingent on the specifics
of the experiment setup.
So even at AI2, there was a paper that was like, well,
it turns out that if you go from DPO to PPO,
you'll get a better result. But then they also
had a paper for Tulu2, where they said, actually,
if you do DPO right, you can do better than PPO.
And so depending on how you execute this,
one can be better than the other.
I'm sure you have experiences reading deep learning
papers and so on, where the results are very fragile.
So maybe the takeaway from all of this that these DPO variants are actually
close enough to the right thing to give you pretty
good performance in many cases.
This core idea of take gradient step in the right direction
and take negative gradient step from the bad stuff
works reasonably well as long as you set the step sizes right.
OK.
I will end with the last few slides on things
to watch out for in RLHF.
So one of the things to watch out for is over optimization.
And this is maybe one of the biggest things.
To give you also historical context,
when InstructGPT came out, and people were very excited
about this, I think there was a very real question
can we RLHF our way to superintelligent systems or whatever?
Maybe we can.
Just collect enough thumbs up, thumbs down.
Turns out that is actually quite challenging.
Because you find that if you try to really push the RLHF
process forward, you'll start overfitting
to your learned reward model.
So the KL regularizer that I talked about
is really critical in a lot of cases in order
to prevent your optimization process
from overfitting your reward model,
at least if your optimization process is very good.
The other thing that I'll talk about is model collapse.
So people have seen lots of times, where RL models have
much less diversity.
They're concentrated on a few different possible outputs.
And this connects back to what I said before right RLHF
models are really no longer modeling
a distribution which comes with its own inherent diversity.
It's a policy that can collapse as
long as it gets a good reward.
So this is another thing that RLHF models have really
struggled with in recent years.
So actually, I'm going to skip this because we're at time.
And I think this entropy and mode collapse thing actually
ends up being quite important even today.
And the GPT-4 era actually was one of the few plots
that OpenAI put out, where they said, actually, we
have a few open problems left.
And one of the open problems they had was,
actually, our models are uncalibrated
after we do RLHF, which you can see in this plot over here.
I don't think anyone has really solved that yet.
The Anthropic folks also had an argument saying, well,
it's naturally uncalibrated.
You could recalibrate sometimes, but not always.
This becomes very important in the next lecture
when we talk about things like RLVR,
where the entropy and exploration is actually
quite critical for the model to explore
all the possible solutions, and to make progress on some
of these very hard problems.
Great.
So to put it all together, RLHF data collection
is also very hard.
I think part of the thing about post-training
is it's very complicated, messy process because a lot of it
is getting good data.
And getting good data is always very difficult.
RLHF algorithms are quite complex.
PPO is especially difficult. I'll talk a little bit about it
next lecture.
Thankfully, we do also have a simpler variant.
They're called GRPO.
That works pretty well.
That's what you'll do in your assignments.
But this is one place where there's been
a lot of recent developments.
Finally, I think, in terms of RLHF,
one of the big, big problems is over-optimization.
And the transition to the next lecture
is going to be: is there rewards where we won't over-optimize
or we can just dumping compute and the model performance just
keeps monotonically getting better.
And that's one of the reasons why what people call
RLVR is just so been so impactful.
Thanks.
I'll see you all Thursday.